Smith K Mulembeta

Accountant, and Auditor

Phone +260-971-417309

Email smthmulembeta@gmail.com

LinkedIn https://linkedin.com/in/smithkalabimulembeta/

I am a passionate Accountant, and Auditor with 4 years of experience in both public and private accounting. I have a strong background in expense management, financial analyses, budgeting, forecasting, and reporting. I am analytical, detail-oriented, and eager to grow in corporate finance within a fast-paced environment.

Top Skills:

- Reporting (4yrs)
- Bank reconciliation (4yrs)
- Revenue management or Accounts receivables management (3yrs)
- Expense management or Accounts payables (3yrs)
- Financial Analysis (4yrs)
- Internal and external audits (3yrs)
- Payroll processing (3yrs)
- Budgeting and Forecasting (3yrs)
- Proficiency in Microsoft Excel and Google Workspace products (5yrs)
- Proficiency in Sage 50, QuickBooks and Sage Online (4yrs)
- Proficiency in NetSuite Cloud Accounting Software (1yr)
- Leadership
- Clear communication

Work History

2021-02present

Audit & Assurance Supervisor / Senior Accountant - 3yrs 8months

WhCorporate chartered Accountants., Lusaka, Lusaka, Zambia | on site

- Collaborating with team members to achieve target results.
- Preparing and analysing financial statements, including balance sheets, income statements, and cashflow statements.
- Ensuring accurate and timely monthly, quarterly, and year-end close processes.
- Maintaining and reconciling general ledger accounts.
- Expense management and accounts receivable, ensuring timely processing of invoices and payments.
- Conducting bank reconciliations and resolving discrepancies.
- Preparing and filing tax returns, ensuring compliance with local regulations.
- Assisting in the preparation of budgets and financial forecasts.
- · Coordinating and supporting internal and external audits.
- Preparing audit schedules and provide necessary documentation and explanations to auditors.
- Implementing and maintaining internal controls to safeguard company assets and ensure accurate financial reporting.
- Performing financial, compliance, and operational audits in accordance with audit plans.

- Evaluating the adequacy and effectiveness of internal controls.
- Reviewing financial statements, accounting records, and other documentation.
- · Verifying the accuracy and completeness of financial records.
- Ensuring company operations comply with applicable laws, regulations, and internal policies.
- Identifying areas of non-compliance and recommending corrective actions.
- Documenting audit procedures and findings in detailed reports through financial Systems.
- Presenting audit findings to management and provide actionable recommendations.
- Identifying potential risks and assessing the effectiveness of risk management processes.
- Recommending strategies through productivity tools to mitigate identified risks.
- Training and mentoring Junior accountants and auditors.
- Working in remote teams and participating in Ad Hoc projects.

Skills: Excel, QuickBooks, Sage 50, Sage Online, Expense management, Financial Analysis, conducting internal and externals audits, Reporting, account reconciliations, Budgeting and Forecasting, payroll processing, Data management and Ability to work independently.

Volunteering activities

2022-05-2022-06

Volunteer Trainer

ZCAS University Audit Class., Lusaka, Lusaka, Zambia

- During my school study break in 2022, I volunteered as a lead trainer to educate my fellow students on the importance of accounting standards (IAS & IFRS) and the distinction between tax evasion and tax avoidance.
- I successfully trained 75 students on the application of accounting standards in audit practice
 and tax computations, covering topics such as asset recognition, classification, impairment,
 depreciation, and other elements of financial statements.

Education background

2018-01-2022

Bachelor's Degree in Accounting & Finance

ZCAS University., Lusaka, Lusaka, Zambia

Certifications

- · CA Zambia Student License
- BKKG Sage Bookkeeping Essentials Partner.
- Internal audit Fundamental Principles
- SBCAC Sage Accounting 2020 Application Specialist Assessment

References

Haggai Simpungwe
Partner | WhCorporate
haggai.simpungwe@whc.co.zm

Ugo Tony AjiH Managing Director | Exponent Bizolution mdexponent@gmail.com